Curriculum vitæ Last update: Feb, 2020

Héctor Ramírez

Data Scientist | PhD in Physics

Brief résumé: I recently earned my PhD in Physics where I specialized in experimental data analysis and mathematical modeling. I led several short and long-term projects in collaboration with colleagues from several institutions in different countries. The results of which I have presented as a speaker in multiple international seminars and conferences. Moreover, I have extended my data analysis techniques with numerous courses on Data Engineering, Data Science and Machine Learning. To mention some skills: SQL, Big Data with PySpark, Supervised and Unsupervised Learning with scikit-learn, Deep Learning with Keras, TensorFlow and PyTorch, Cloud Computing with AWS, Natural Language Processing, etc.

Contact (+34)693012381 □ — Mail 🔽 — LinkedIn 🛅 — GitHub 🗘 — Webpage 🔇

Residence Valencia, Spain (with Spanish work permit).

Birth and Nationality | May 20th, 1990 — Mexican.

Education

PhD in Physics | University of Valencia, Spain.

2015-2019 Dissertation: 'Noncanonical Approaches to Inflation'

MA in Advanced University of Valencia, Spain.

Physics 2013-2014 | Dissertation: 'The Hu-Sawicki Model of Modified Gravity'

BA in Physics University of Veracruz, Mexico.

2008-2013 Dissertation: 'Quantum Chaos in the Dicke Model'

2012 University of Valencia (Academic exchange semester), Spain.

Additional training

I have been continuously learning **Data Engineering**, **Data Science** and **Machine Learning** techniques following the course plan by **DataCamp**, where I have completed more than 40 courses.

■ Professional Experience

International projects

I have done research placements in the UK, Japan, Italy and in the Fermilab National Laboratory (USA), where I led short-and long-term collaborative projects and presented results as international speaker.

Apr - Jun, 2018	Institute of Cosmology and Gravitation (ICG), University of Portsmouth Portsmouth, UK.
Jan - Mar, 2018	Kavli Institute for the Physics and Mathematics of the Universe (IPMU), The University of Tokyo
May - Aug, 2017	Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab) & Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics – The University of Chicago
Apr - Jun, 2015	Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) Trieste, Italy.

Teaching

I have taught undergraduate courses managed by the Department of Theoretical Physics at the University of Valencia during the last four academic years—about 45 hours in the classroom (groups of around 15 students) + class preparation, per academic year.

Classical	Teaching Assistant (2017-2019): Resolution of problems, examinations, evaluation
Mechanics	of teaching contents and elaboration of teaching material.
Introductory Physics	Teaching Assistant (2015-2018): Resolution of problems, occasional lectures, examinations and grading.

Journal referee

I have refereed scientific articles for the journals **Physical Review Letters** and **Physical Review D**, both from the American Physical Society (USA).

Skills

Computer

Programming | Scientific Python (NumPy, SciPy, pandas, GetDist, etc.), Mathematica.

Visualization Matplotlib, seaborn, bokeh.

Machine Learning scikit-learn, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, XGBoost, Natural Language Processing.

Database SQL, PySpark.
Web HTML, CSS.

Other Git, Bash scripting, Conda, Amazon Web Services (S3, SNS, Rekognition).

Languages

Spanish: Native; English: Fluent; French: B2 level. I have also taken German and Italian courses.

Sports

Highly active in organizing, managing and participating in sport teams, mainly on **football soccer**—I have joined and organized football teams in every place I have done a research stay.

Awards and Fellowships

2015 - 2019	FPI Research fellow by the <i>Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competitiveness</i> (MINECO), Spanish Government.
Jul - Sep, 2014	Research scholarship granted by the University of Valencia
Jan - Jul, 2012	Grant for an abroad academic exchange semester by the University of Veracruz Carried out at the Faculty of Physics, <i>University of Valencia</i> .
2009 - 2011	Faculty award (x2) due to academic excellence University of Veracruz

Publications

A total of **8** research articles published either in **Physical Review D** (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields — Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.568] (x5); **Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics** (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields – Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.734] (x2); **Physics of the Dark Universe** (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.) [Impact factor: 5.425] (x1).

My total list of publications can be found in my Inspire page: http://inspirehep.net/author/profile/H.Ramirez.1

Talks

Conference talks 5 talks in Valencia, Paris, Teruel (Spain), Kyoto (Japan) and Portsmouth (UK).

Seminar talks | 13 talks in Valencia (x2), Paris (x2), Tokyo, London, Portsmouth (UK), New York,

Chicago, UC Berkeley (USA), Schladming (Austria) and Veracruz (Mexico).

Details about my talks can be found in https://hectoramirez.github.io/Files/CV/Talks.pdf .

■ References

Dr. Olga Mena Requejo

Instituto de Física Corpuscular (IFIC)



Prof. Nick E. Mavromatos

King's College London



Prof. David Wands

University of Portsmouth



Prof. Shinji Tsujikawa

Tokyo University of Science

